Guide to the Charles G. Wright Collection of Big Little Books
Charles G. Wright Collection of Big Little Books
1933-1943
1933 1943
Wright Charles G. Charles Gerald 1930-
RBC 00001
Big Little Books and Better Little Books published, 1933-1943, by Whitman Publishing Company of Racine, Wisconsin, and books of similar format published, 1934-1941, by the Saalfield Publishing Company, Engel-van Wiseman and Rand McNally.
Charles G. Wright is Professor Emeritus of Entomology at North Carolina State University. Big Little Books were inexpensive children's books about 3 1/2" x 4 1/2" x 1 1/2" in size. They were first published in 1932 by Whitman Publishing Company of Racine, Wisconsin. There was a captioned picture opposite each page of text. Most of them were based on radio, comic strips, or motion pictures. Other publishing companies which produced similar books were Dell, Engel-van Wiseman, Fawcett, Goldsmith, Lynn, Ottenheimer, Saalfield, Waldman, and World Syndicate.
2.5 linear feet
North Carolina State University Libraries, Special Collections Research Center
Gift of Charles G. Wright, 2003 October.
The collection is organized into five series: Western, Characters from the Comics, War and Military, Adventure, and Other.
Charles G. Wright, Professor Emeritus of Entomology at North Carolina State University, was born on 1930 June 12 in Boynton, Pa. He received an B.S. in 1951 and M.S. in 1953 from the University of Maryland and a Ph.D. in entomology from North Carolina State University in 1958. Wright was employed as an entomologist with Wilson Pest Control from 1958 to 1963 and then by North Carolina State University from 1963 until his retirement.
In 1932 Whitman Publishing Company of Racine, Wisconsin began publishing small, fat books they called Big Little Books. Most Big Little Books were about 3 1/2" x 4 1/2" x 1 1/2" in size. There was a captioned picture opposite each page of text. These inexpensive books for children originally sold for a dime. Most of them were based on radio, comic strips, or motion pictures. In 1938, Whitman changed the name of its series to Better Little Books. The last Better Little Book was published in 1949. Other publishing companies which produced similar books were Dell, Engel-van Wiseman, Fawcett, Goldsmith, Lynn, Ottenheimer, Saalfield, Waldman, and World Syndicate.
Big Little Books and Better Little Books, illustrated children's books published, 1933-1943, by Whitman Publishing Company of Racine, Wisconsin, and books of similar format published, 1934-1941, by the Saalfield Publishing Company, Engel-van Wiseman and Rand McNally.
Young Chic 1901-1973; Young Lyman; Winterbotham R. R. Russell Robert 1904-1971; Wright Charles G. Charles Gerald 1930-; Striker Fran 1903-1962; West Wilton; Beach Rex 1877-1949; Beatty Jerome; Branner Martin Michael b. 1888; Breitigam Gerald; Nowlan Phil; Morgan Leon; Segar E. C. Elzie Crisler 1894-1938; Penfield Thomas; Marshall Robert; Marsh Norman; Millis Mark; Martinek Frank V. Frank Victor b. 1895; George Gerry; Forrest Hal; Hess Sol b. 1885; Grey Zane 1872-1939; Caniff Milton Arthur 1907-1988; Byrnes Gene 1889-1974; Disney Walt 1901-1966; Curwood James Oliver 1878-1927; Big little books; Illustrated children's books
- Western, 1935-1940; 1935 1940; 0.75 linear feet
  - Billy of Bar-Zero / Marshall, Robert / Akron, Ohio: Saalfield Publishing Company, 1940. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dan of the Lazy L, a range war story / Millis, Mark / Akron, Ohio, New York: The Saalfield Publishing Company, 1939. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Junior Nebb on the Diamond Bar Ranch, based on the famous newspaper strip "The Nebbs," Big little book no. 1422 / Hess, Sol / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1938. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lone Ranger and his horse Silver, Big little book no. 1181 / [Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1935]. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Missing title page and other pages before p.9
  - Lone Ranger and the black shirt highwayman with Silver and Tonto, based on the famous radio adventure program, Better little book no. 1450 / Striker, Fran / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1939. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lone Ranger and the red renegades, based on the famous radio program, Better little book no. 1489 / Striker, Fran / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1939. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lone Ranger and the secret killer with Silver and Tonto, based on the famous radio adventure series by Fran Striker, Big little book no. 1431 / Wilson, Buck / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1937. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lone Ranger and the vanishing herd with Silver and Tonto, based on the famous radio adventure series by Fran Striker, Big little book no. 1196 / Wilson, Buck / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1936. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rex, king of wild horses in "Stampede" based on the motion picture "Wild Horse Stampede," a Columbia picture / Gerry, George / New York, New York: Engel-van Wiseman Incorporated, 1935. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Shooting sherriffs of the Wild West, Big little book [no. 1195] / Morgan, Leon / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1936. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Tom Mix plays a lone hand, Big little book no. 1173 / West, Wilton / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1935. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Zane Grey's King of the Royal Mounted and the great jewel mystery, based on the famous newspaper strip, Better little book no. 1486 / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1937. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Zane Grey's King of the Royal Mounted gets his man, based on the famous adventure strip, Big little book no. 1452 / Grey, Zane / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1938. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Characters from the Comics, 1934-1941; 1934 1941; 0.75 linear feet
  - Blondie and Baby Dumpling, based on the famous comic strip, Big little book no. 1415 / Young, Chic / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1937. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Donald Duck off the beam! Better little book no. 1438 / Disney, Walt / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1943. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    With "Movies" of Donald flip book feature
  - Donald Duck sees stars! Better little book no. 1422 / Disney, Walt / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1941. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mickey Mouse and Bobo the Elephant, Big little book no. 1160 / Disney, Walt / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, [1935]. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Missing title page and other pages before p. 25
  - Mickey Mouse and Pluto the Racer, Big little book no. 1128 / Disney, Walt / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1936. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mickey Mouse in the treasure hunt, Big little book no. 1401 / Disney, Walt / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1941. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    With "Movies" of Pluto flip book feature
  - Mickey Mouse runs his own newspaper, Big little book no. 1409 / Disney, Walt / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1937. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Perry Winkle and the Rinkeydinks get a horse, based on the famous comic strip, "Winnie Winkle the Breadwinner," Better little book no. 1487 / Branner, Martin / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1938. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Popeye in Puddleburg, adapted from the famous newspaper comic series drawn by E.C. Segar / Akron, Ohio New York: The Saalfield Publishing Company, 1934. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Wimpy the hamburger eater, based on the famous comic strip "Thimble theatre starring Popeye," Big little book no. 1458 / Segar / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1938. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- War and Military, 1935-1943; 1935 1943; 0.5 linear feet
  - Allen Pike of the Parachute Squad U.S.A., Better little book no. 1481 / Winterbotham, R.R. / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1941. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - America on guard: Army Navy Marine Corps facts, insignia, uniforms / Penfield, Thomas / Chicago: Rand McNally & Company, 1941. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Captain Robb of Dirigible ZR-90 and the Disappearing Zeppelin, Better little book no. 1464 / Winterbotham, R.R. / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1941. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Don Winslow, U.S.N., Big little book no. 1107 / Martinek, Lieut.-Comdr. Frank volumes / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1935. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Keep 'em flying U.S.A. for America's victory, Better little book no. 1420 / Winterbotham, R.R. / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1943. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    With flip book feature
  - Keep 'em flying U.S.A. for America's victory, Better little book no. 1420 / Winterbotham, R.R. / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1943. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Wings for America fighting planes of the U.S.A. / Penfield, Thomas / Chicago: Rand McNally & Company, 1941. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Adventure, 1934-1939; 1934 1939; 0.5 linear feet
  - Buck Rogers on the moons of Saturn, Big little book no. 1143 / Nowlan, Phil / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1934. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Dan Dunn Crime Operative 48 and the Crime Master, based on the famous newspaper strip, Big little book 1171 / Marsh, Norman / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1937. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - James Oliver Curwood's Kazan in "Revenge of the North," the story of a great dog, Big little book 1105 / Curwood, James Oliver / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1937. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Rex Beach's Jaragu of the jungle, adventures among the Indians of Central America, Big little book no. 1424 / Beach, Rex / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1937. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Tailspin Tommy hunting for pirate gold, Big little book / Forrest, Hal / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1935. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Terry and the pirates and the giant's vengeance based on the famous adventure strip, Better little book no. 1446 / Caniff, Milton / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1939. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Terry and the pirates shipwrecked on a desert island, Big little book no. 1412 / Caniff, Milton / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1938. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Tim Tyler's luck, adventures in the ivory patrol, based on the famous adventure strip, Big little book no. 1140 / Young, Lyman / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1937. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Tim Tyler's luck, the plot of the exiled king, based on the famous adventure strip, Better little book no. 1479 / Young, Lyman / Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, 1939. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Other, 1933-1935; 1933 1935; 0.25 linear feet
  - Curley Harper at Lakespur, from the famous newspaper cartoon drawn by Lyman Young / Breitigam, Gerald / New York, N.Y.: Lynn Publishing Co., Inc., 1935. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Reg'lar fellers, Big little book no. 754 / Byrnes, Gene / [Racine, Wisconsin: Whitman Publishing Company, ], [1933]. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Missing title page and pages before p. 11
  - Story of Will Rogers / Beatty, Jerome / Akron, Ohio New York: The Saalfield Publishing Company, 1935. (Box 5, Folder 8)